{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One leader of this country wanted to create a buffer state called “Intermarium” out of his country and its neighbors. This country, which lost a plebiscite awarding control of the Teschen district, defeated an invading force under Marshal Tukachevsky; the key battle of that campaign took place in this country’s capital and was nicknamed the “Miracle on the Vistula”. For ten points, name this country led by Jozef Pilsudski.",
      "answer": "Poland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This initiative supplanted Directive 1067 and was in turn replaced by the Mutual Security Agency. This initiative was adopted after Herbert Hoover noted that a “pastoral state” would be the outcome of the opposing Morgenthau Plan. Greece and Turkey were the first countries to adopt this plan, and Joseph Stalin ordered Warsaw Pact nations not to accept its money. Harry Truman’s Secretary of State names, for ten points, what American plan that offered economic aid to Europe after World War II?",
      "answer": [
        "Marshall Plan or European Recovery Program",
        "ERP"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man violated the sovereignty of a neighboring country by recognizing the Act of Free Choice assemblies, and he turned the Golkar group into a personal political machine. The Santa Cruz Massacre occurredaspartofthisman’sattemptstocrackdownonFRETILIN,arevolutionarygroupinabreakaway region of his country. This man recruited the so-called “Berkeley Mafia” to create economic growth in a regime he called the “New Order.” For ten points, name this politician who succeeded Sukarno as leader of Indonesia.",
      "answer": "Suharto"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a novel written in this language, Bartlebooth spends a decade learning how to paint before going on a trip around the world. Another novel in this language was written entirely without the use of the letter E as part of the Oulipo movement. Life: A User’s Manual and A Void were written by Georges Perec in, for ten points, what language in which The Stranger and No Exit were written by Jean-Paul Sartre and Albert Camus?",
      "answer": "French"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this year, the USS Vandalia faced off against German ships in Samoa until it was destroyed by a cyclone. The Enabling Act was signed during it to split the Dakota Territory, and the “Sooners” and “Boomers” flooded to settle Oklahoma in this year. The Great Johnstown Flood devastated Pennsylvania during it, the first year where the “Billion Dollar Congress” met. For ten points, name this year in which Benjamin Harrison began his term as US President.",
      "answer": "1889"
    },
    {
      "question": "Shuck Yee invented a machine to mass produce these things, which Seiichi Kito claims were inspired by the Omikuji tradition. A tea garden was said to have been the venue where the first of these were served in the 1890’s; that example was allegedly baked in San Francisco. Sesame seed oil is generally used to make, for ten points, what foodstuff that was notably not invented in China and contains a supposed prophecy on a paper slip?",
      "answer": "fortune cookie"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s St. Anne’s Church contains the tombs of three brothers of the Fugger family, whose banking enterprise operated here. The painter Hans Holbein the Younger was born in this city, where a 1555 peace treaty was signed to end a war between the Schmalkaldic League and Charles V. Charles had earlier convened a Diet in this city where Philip Melancthon helped draft a namesake Lutheran Confession. For ten points, name this Free Imperial City in Bavaria.",
      "answer": "Augsburg"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. This action, as proposed in UN Resolution 181, was rejected by one side of the discussion. Haganah and the Irgun agitated for this action, whose early advocates included Theodor Herzl. The Balfour Declaration established British support for this action, whose eventual realization led to an outpouring of hundreds of thousands of refugees from the West Bank. A 1948 war accompanied, for ten points, what geopolitical action that followed the end of the British Mandate for Palestine?",
      "answer": [
        "creation of Israel",
        "equivalent descriptions",
        "descriptions of separate states for Jews and Palestinians or Jews and Arabs, etc. in Israel/Middle East"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man ordered that the government store its funds in vaults rather than banks as part of the independent treasury he created. The popularity of this man plummeted after Charles Ogle accused him of lavish spending in the Gold Spoon Oration. This man was forced to carry out his predecessor’s Specie Circular executive order, leading to the Panic of 1837. For ten points, name this Democratic president, a Dutch-American from New York.",
      "answer": "Martin van Buren"
    },
    {
      "question": "An interregnum in this empire was resolved at the Battle of Camurlu. A rebellion against this empire was led by one of its former generals, Skanderbeg. This country’s government was known as the Sublime Porte and was once based in Edirne. One ruler of this country, Bayezid the Thunderbolt, was captured by Timur at the Battle of Ankara. For ten points, name this empire that was led by Murad II and other sultans from modern Turkey.",
      "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A governor of this state was chairman of Hillary Clinton’s 2008 bid for the presidency and controversially tried to restore the voting rights of more than 200,000 felons in an executive order that was later overturned. Democratic blocs in Fairfax and Arlington counties have made this state increasingly blue in recent elections. A senator from this state was chosen as the running mate for Hillary Clinton in the 2016 presidential election. Tim Kaine represents, for ten points, what state where state law prevents governors from serving consecutive terms in Richmond?",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This aforementioned governor of Virginia was succeeded by Ralph Northam in 2018.",
        "answer": "Terry McAuliffe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader passed the Law of Cooperatives, allowing private enterprises to be established, and adopted a policy of non-intervention that became known as the Sinatra doctrine. This leader became the target of a coup led by the Gang of Eight after his reforms were deemed too radical. This architect of glasnost and perestroika was challenged by Ronald Reagan to tear down the Berlin Wall. For ten points, name this final leader of the Soviet Union.",
        "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Glasnost and perestroika were Gorbachev’s chosen names for his efforts to reform the Communist Party.GivethecommonEnglishtranslationforeither ofthetwoterms;glasnosthastwoequallyprominent translations.",
        "answer": [
          "openness",
          "transparency",
          "restructuring",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man declared that “love to my country actuates... my conduct, however it may appear inconsistent” in defending himself in a letter addressed “To the Inhabitants of America.” This man was forced to flee on the Vulture after his associate, John Andre, was captured. For ten points, name this traitorous Continental Army general who attempted to turn West Point over to the British.",
        "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Arnold helped sabotage West Point by weakening its defenses, including by failing to maintain a protective chain that spanned this river, on which West Point is located.",
        "answer": "Hudson River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Elections in this country were held after the June Struggle led to the establishment of the Sixth Republic. A student uprising in 1960 led to the overthrow of this country’s first ruler, Syngman Rhee. This country signed an armistice at Panmunjom, establishing its northern border as a demilitarized zone at the 38th parallel. For ten points, name this country bordered to the north by a dictatorship ruled by the Kim family.",
        "answer": [
          "South Korea or the Republic of Korea",
          "ROK"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This first female President of South Korea was impeached in 2016 on corruption charges.",
        "answer": "Park Geun-hye"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This field of study was founded during the Dartmouth Conference. The failure of initiatives like Japan’s fifth generation project was due to financial setbacks in this field during its namesake “winters.” John Searle dissented against the main argument of a paper in this field beginning “Can Machines Think?” The Turing Test uses questions to discern between the cognitive abilities of humans and computers in, for ten points, what area of computer science?",
        "answer": "artificial intelligence or AI"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Searle’s 1980 paper about the Chinese Room Argument divided artificial intelligence into these two types, named for a machine’s ability to perform general and specific actions.",
        "answer": "strong and weak AI"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A tariff named for a politician from this state was altered 12 years later with the Payne-Aldrich Tariff; that longest-lasting tariff in American history was named after this state’s representative Nelson Dingley. Another politician from this state left the Democratic Party in 1856 after it supported the Kansas-Nebraska Act and became the first Republican Vice President; that native of this state served in a border struggle between this state and New Brunswick. For ten points, name this US state, the site of the Aroostook War in New England.",
        "answer": "Maine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This native of Maine served as Abraham Lincoln’s first Vice President.",
        "answer": "Hannibal Hamlin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This language’s 7th century Kufic style of calligraphy is based on straight lines and right angles. Like other languages in its family, including Hebrew, this language builds words around three-consonant roots. The “Modern Standard” variety of this language is commonly used in literature and the news, despite the wide variance in dialects. This language’s writing system lends its name to the term abjad, for an alphabet without vowels. For ten points, name this primary language spoken in Morocco, Egypt, and Qatar.",
        "answer": "Arabic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Arabic and Hebrew belong to this five-millennia-old language family, which also includes Amharic, Syriac, and Maltese.",
        "answer": "Semitic languages"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A commander in this conflict successfully concluded a defense of his territory in the Treaty of Hubertusburg; that man nearly committed suicide after a loss at Kunersdorf, though he had earlier won a great victory at Rossbach in this war. This war was preceded by a change in alliances, in which France allied with Austria and Britain allied with Prussia, and it was ended by a 1763 Treaty of Paris. Frederick the Great participated in, for ten points, what expansive conflict that included the French and Indian War?",
        "answer": "Seven Years War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The change in alliances prior to the Seven Years War is historically known by this name.",
        "answer": "Diplomatic Revolution"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Hurricanes",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "2005 hurricane that killed over 1,800 people and devastated New Orleans.",
          "answer": "Hurricane Katrina"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. territory where thousands were killed by Hurricane Maria in 2017.",
          "answer": "Puerto Rico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Agency of the Department of Homeland Security responsible for responding to hurricanes and other disasters.",
          "answer": "FEMA or Federal Emergency Management Agency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician whose failure leading that agency in 2005 led President Bush to tell him “you’re doing a heck of a job.”",
          "answer": [
            "Michael Brown",
            "“Brownie, you’re doing a heck of a job”"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas port city destroyed in 1900 by the deadliest hurricane in US history.",
          "answer": "Galveston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Atlantic hurricane that caused the closure of Atlantic City in 2012.",
          "answer": "Hurricane Sandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pair of civil engineers who, in 1971, developed a scale for classifying hurricanes.",
          "answer": "Herbert Saffir and William Simpson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holiday on which a record setting hurricane struck Florida in 1935.",
          "answer": "1935 Labor Day hurricane"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Charlemagne",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire that traced its lineage back to Charlemagne’s coronation in the year 800 AD and dissolved in 1806.",
          "answer": [
            "Holy Roman Empire",
            "HRE"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Holy day on which Charlemagne was crowned in 800 AD.",
          "answer": "Christmas Day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Germanic group he Christianized; with the Angles, these people co-name the group that settled Britain after Roman influence waned.",
          "answer": "Saxons"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Charlemagne who became the first Carolingian King of the Franks in 751.",
          "answer": "Pepin the Short"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Charlemagne’s empire and the site of his burial tomb.",
          "answer": "Aachen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scholar in Charlemagne’s court who wrote the biography Vita Karoli Magni.",
          "answer": "Einhard or Einhart"
        },
        {
          "question": "782 massacre of nearly 5,000 Saxons ordered by Charlemagne.",
          "answer": "Massacre of Verden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian city where Charlemagne besieged Desiderius and the Lombards in 774, after which he became their king.",
          "answer": "Pavia"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mongol Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where the Mongols established the Yuan Dynasty, which ended the Song Dynasty.",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in modern Iraq sacked by Mongols under Hulagu Khan in 1258.",
          "answer": "Baghdad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Common term for the Nizari Ismailis, a sect the Mongols crushed in the 13th century; their name now generally refers to hired killers.",
          "answer": [
            "Assassins",
            "Asasiyyun"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Adjective that describes the “History of the Mongols” written in the 13th century, as well as Procopius’ history of the Byzantine Empire.",
          "answer": "Secret History"
        },
        {
          "question": "East Slavic state conquered by the Mongols in 1240; its leaders included Vladimir the Great.",
          "answer": "Kievan Rus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Splinter khanate founded by Batu Khan that ruled the northwest region of the Mongol Empire.",
          "answer": [
            "Golden Horde",
            "Ulus of Jochi",
            "Kipchak Khanate"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the empire from 1235 to 1260, until Kublai Khan moved to Shangdu.",
          "answer": "Karakorum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Descendent of Genghis Khan who reunited two splinter khanates in 1382 and lost a war against Tamerlane.",
          "answer": "Tokhtamysh"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was advised by Mikhail Speransky during his reform of the government and Aleksey Arakcheev during his military reforms. This leader’s failures as commander in chief led him to appoint Mikhail (20 pts)",
        "Kutuzov to lead his army. Confusion over who should succeed this man led to the liberal (10 pts)",
        "Decembrist revolt. This ruler formed the Holy Alliance with Austria and Prussia to preserve Europe after the Congress of Vienna. For ten points, name this Russian tsar who led his country through the Napoleonic Wars."
      ],
      "answer": "Alexander I of Russia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country celebrates the feast of Epiphany with a celebration called Timkat. A community of Jews from this country called Beta Israel claims to be descended from the Queen of (20 pts)",
        "Sheba. This country is home to ancient rock-hewn churches at Lalibela. It’s not Jamaica, but (10 pts)",
        "Rastafarians regard a former monarch of this country to be the Second Coming of Christ. For ten points, name this country whose Christian church claims to have the original Ark of the Covenant, an African country with capital at Addis Ababa."
      ],
      "answer": "Ethiopia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man supposedly introduced his friend and former classmate James Madison to his future wife Dolley Payne. Anthony Merry and James Wilkinson were alleged co-conspirators in this man’s plot to take over (20 pts)",
        "land in the southwest to form his own country. This man represented New York in the Senate after winning an election against Philip (10 pts)",
        "Schuyler [sky-ler], the father-in-law of a man who thwarted this man’s presidential ambitions by backing Thomas Jefferson in the election of 1800. For ten points, name this politician who won a duel against his rival, Alexander Hamilton."
      ],
      "answer": "Aaron Burr"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One historian claims that the organizers of this event dealt with their opponents by “placing them in shackles, poking them with knives.” Toghon Temur failed to put down this event, which involved a group that was created by Guo Zixing. (20 pts)",
        "Zhu Yuanzhang was one of the main leaders of this event, which was inspired by the teachings of the White (10 pts)",
        "Lotus sect. This 14th century event resulted in the rise of the Hongwu Emperor and the overthrow of the Yuan Dynasty. For ten points, name this rebellion named for the colored headcloth of its rebels."
      ],
      "answer": "Red Turban Rebellion or Hongjin Qiyi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This is the most populous city founded by James Robertson, who helped lead the Watauga Association. The inhabitant of a famous residence in this city married a woman he met here named Rachel (20 pts)",
        "Donelson. The Hermitage is located in this city, where a $1 million grant led to the 1873 creation of a (10 pts)",
        "university named for a New York tycoon. Andrew Jackson lived much of his life in, for ten points, what city which is home to Vanderbilt University, located in Tennessee?"
      ],
      "answer": "Nashville"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country was defended by qenderzjarri forts designed by Josif Zigali and the Sigurimi secret police. Roughly 5.7 bunkers per square kilometer were constructed in this country, whose government justified it as preparation against a joint (20 pts)",
        "NATO-Warsaw Pact invasion. After a disagreement, Nikita Khrushchev withdrew grain shipments from this country, which broke with its last ally, China, over the Three Worlds Theory. This country, the (10 pts)",
        "poorest in Europe during the 1980s, proclaimed itself the world’s first atheist state. For ten points, name this isolationist Balkan nation once led by Enver Hoxha [ho-cha]."
      ],
      "answer": "Albania"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country birthed a tradition of musical composition known as “kuchkism.” Numerous works written in this country, including Ruslan and Lyudmila and Kashchey the Immortal, use the (20 pts)",
        "whole tone scale to give a sense of foreboding evil, a technique developed by a group that included Cesar Cui and was led by Mily (10 pts)",
        "Balakirev. For ten points, name this country where nationalism was promoted by The Mighty Handful, a group of five composers including Modest Mussorgsky, Alexander Borodin, and Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov."
      ],
      "answer": "Russia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle may have begun when Johnston Pettigrew’s party was send to search for shoes. A clash at Brandy Station took place just before this battle, depriving one side of (20 pts)",
        "JEB Stuart’s cavalry. The 20th Maine regiment was led by Joshua Chamberlain in defending Little (10 pts)",
        "Round Top during this battle, which culminated in an ill-fated attack on Cemetery Ridge by George Pickett’s forces. For ten points, name this 1863 battle in Pennsylvania known as the turning point of the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Gettysburg"
    }
  ]
}